Finding Aid for Computing Center (University of Michigan) records, 1952-1996
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Computing Center (University of Michigan) records 1952-1996, 1959-1987
University of Michigan. Computing Center.
1 GB
42.5 linear feet
9551 Bimu 2
Established in 1959 to operate academic computing facility and provide computing services for faculty and students. Developed Michigan Terminal System (MTS) operating system and other software for mainframe computers. Merged into University of Michigan Information Technology Division in 1985. Administrative records including minutes, correspondence, budget material, and reports, documenting management of the center, purchase and operation of mainframe computers, development of MTS and other software, and computer networks. Also includes paper and digital MTS distribution documentation.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records (Donor No. 7873 ) were transferred in several accessions from the Computing Center in 1994, the Information Technology Division in 1996, and former employees in 2011
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The Computing Center records are open for research use with the exception of several files of personnel records which are restricted in accordance with university policy and applicable law. The restricted files are located in Box 43.
The Computing Center record group includes restricted material in the following categories:
Personnel Related Records -- Boxes 43
The University of Michigan Computing Center was established as an independent center within the Horace Rackham School of Graduate Studies on July 1, 1959. Prior to this it was part of the Statistical and Computing Laboratory of the Graduate School. In 1965 the Computing Center was placed under the Vice President for Research. With the appointment of the Vice Provost for Information Technology and creation of the Information Technology Division (ITD) in 1985, the Computing Center was made a unit of ITD.
The function of the Computing Center was to provide computing services for the academic and research needs of the entire university campus, to operate and maintain mainframe computing facilities, and to engage in research and development of computer software and hardware systems. In the early 1980s, the Computing Center became involved in the introduction of personal computers on campus and the development of local, regional and national computer networks.
Dr. Robert F.C. Bartels was named the first director of the Computing Center, serving until 1978. Aaron Finerman became director in 1978 and was succeeded in turn by Carolyn Autrey-Hunley in 1986. The Computing Center's first facility was located in remodeled space in the North University Building at 1205 North University Avenue. The Center moved to a new facility on North Campus in 1971. The North University Building (NUB) location became the first of a number of public access computing sites operated by the Computing Center.
The first digital computing machine at the university was built by the Willow Run Laboratory under sponsorship of the Wright Air Development Center of the U.S. Air Force. The MIDAC (Michigan Digital Automatic Computer) became operational in 1953. It was the second such computer in the Midwest and was used primarily for government sponsored research, with only limited access for instructional use. Nevertheless, a number of faculty and graduate students did receive training on the MIDAC. Under the direction of Professor John Carr, several automatic programming systems were developed for the MIDAC, including MAGIC (Michigan Automatic General Integrated Computation) and EASIAC (Easy Instruction Automatic Computer.) This marked the beginning of a tradition of operating system and programming language development at the university. The Air Force, which retained ownership of MIDAC, removed the machine from campus in 1958.
In 1956 the university administration approved the installation of an IBM 650 in the Statistical Research Lab in the Rackham Building under the auspices of the IBM Educational Contribution Program. Statistical Lab staff, led by Bruce Arden and Bob Graham developed the Generalized Algebraic Translator (GAT) programming language and compiler, a relatively easy to use language that greatly expanded the user community on campus and at other sites where it was installed. The IBM 650 was in service at the Statistical Lab through September of 1959.
An ad hoc committee chaired by university Vice President William Stirton was formed in 1956/57 to consider the need for a major computational facility for instructional and research use. The recommendations of this committee led to the establishment of the Computing Center. In 1957 the committee considered bids from IBM, Univac Division of Sperry Rand, and Burroughs for the installation of a new, more powerful computer. The IBM bid was accepted and a model 704 was delivered to the North University Building in July, 1959 and became operational in August.
Aug. 1959 - Aug. 1961 IBM 704
Jan. 1961 - Aug. 1962 IBM 709
Sept. 1962 - July 1968 IBM 7090
May 1966 - March 1967 IBM 360/50
March 1967 - July 1968 IBM 360/Half Duplex 67
Aug. 1968 - 1975 IBM 360/Full Duplex 67
Jan. 1975 - Sept. 1975 IBM 370/168
The Computing Center staff developed operating systems and languages for each of the machines including MAD (Michigan Algorithm Decoder) for the 704, 709 and 7090 series as well as the UM Executive System (UMES) for the 7090. The limited memory available to the IBM 7090 and the high cost of its operation demanded the use of "batch processing," in which programs were run immediately after one another with minimal human intervention. Batch processing ensured that the university's expensive computing resources were used cost-effectively, but did so at the price of requiring users to wait hours or days for project results. However, in 1966 new developments in virtual memory architecture inspired the staff of the Computing Center to draft a proposal for a terminal-oriented, timesharing operating system that would allow users to interact with their programs and receive immediate results.1
The Computing Center staff took their timesharing proposal to IBM which led, after a period of close collaboration, to the development of a one-of-a-kind IBM System 360/66M computer ('M' for 'Michigan'). The Computing Center entered into an agreement with IBM to assist in development of the Time Sharing System (TSS), an operating system that would take advantage of the multi-processing features of the 360/67. When project delays prevented IBM from delivering software to support the new hardware's timesharing capability, Michael T. Alexander and Donald W. Boettner led the development of an in-house timesharing operating system, the Michigan Terminal System (MTS). The low level supervisor or kernel of the system was the UM Multiprogramming Supervisor (UMMPS) which controlled the execution of multiple instances of "job programs," one of which was MTS which made timesharing possible.
MTS was released to the UM campus in May, 1967 and the first remote connections were established at the Dearborn campus in 1969. The Computing Center's facilities in the North University Building were remodeled and expanded several times between 1959 and 1968 to accommodate new machines and greatly increased demand for services. Construction of a new building on North Campus began in 1969 and the Computing Center moved to the new facility in April, 1971. The North University Building facilities were converted to a faculty/student computing site with remote terminal connections to the mainframe on North Campus. Other computing sites were later established at the Michigan Union and other campus locations. By 1970 the system could support 58 simultaneous users on nearly 200 terminals providing access to MTS on the UM campus and from other universities. While MTS had little difficulty responding to requests for 100,000 jobs per month or more, such demands were growing beyond the capacity of the IBM 360/67 computers on which it ran. The Computing Center preferred the superior speed, reliability, and lower cost of the compatible Amdahl 470V/6 computer. U-M was the first university to use the Amdahl computer, installing serial number P2 during the summer of 1975. Other universities soon migrated to Amdahl and these systems (470V/6, 470V/7, 470V/8, and 5860, running the MTS operating system) would remain a part of the UM computing infrastructure through the mid-1980s.
In addition to the University of Michigan and the University of British Columbia, there were five other member institutions of the MTS Consortium: the University of Alberta, Wayne State University, the Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute, Simon Fraser University, and NUMAC ("Northumbrian Universities Multiple Access Computer," a collaboration among the University of Newcastle upon Tyne, Durham University, and Newcastle Polytechnic). Each of the member institutions played a significant part in the development of MTS, particularly in the design, implementation, and testing of features and services. Other notable users of MTS included Michigan State University, Hewlett-Packard, and NASA's Goddard Space Flight Center.
In the early 1970s a parallel initiative, the Michigan Educational Research Information Triad (MERIT) linked the computer systems of the University of Michigan, Michigan State University, and Wayne State University. The MERIT network was independent of MTS, but in practice the two projects were closely associated, and the University of Michigan provided all hosting and staff support for the new network. By the late 1970s, MERIT had begun to expand to other Michigan universities as part of its mission to provide advanced and expensive computer resources to smaller institutions that could not otherwise afford them. Services provided by the MERIT network would include access to the Telnet network by 1976 as well as access to the internet in 1985. Communication processing technology developed for MERIT would lead to the creation of UMnet in 1983.
MTS also provided innovative services. In 1975 graduate student Robert Parnes created CONFER, an early conferencing system for private electronic mail exchange, open or invitation-only group discussion on MTS and on other systems linked to MTS via the Merit network. Email service to remote users on other systems was added in September 1983 when MTS joined the MAILNET project, a joint effort by sixteen universities and EDUCOM (the precursor to EDUCAUSE). The increasing popularity of microcomputers in the early 1980s also led the Computing Center staff to develop programs which would allow the use of Apple II and IBM PC computers as terminals on the MTS system.
The development of popular features, such as remote access from other networks, added to the growing demand placed on MTS by students and faculty. In 1985, a second system was secured for the increased use. This second system was named "UB" or "U-Blue" to distinguish it from the first system, which was retroactively designated "UM" or "U-Maize." A third MTS system was created for the UM Department of Human Genetics.
By the 1980s, the introduction of personal computers led to a movement away from centralized, mainframe computing towards a more distributed computing environment. The increasing popularity of microcomputers coupled with other trends in computer technology during that time eventually led to the replacement of MTS largely by Unix-based networked servers with TCP/IP support for internet connectivity. Phase out of MTS, the heart of the university's academic computing system for more than two decades, began in the late 1980s and end-user support ended in June 1996; the UM systems themselves were shut down on May 30, 1997. The last member of the MTS Consortium to have an MTS system in operation was Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute, which shut down its system in June 1999.
In 1985 the Computing Center was merged into the Information Technology Division, a new unit created in 1984 to focus on network development, provide support for microcomputers, and orient users to a networked environment. In what was considered a "major appointment," Douglas Van Houweling became University of Michigan vice provost for information technology, a newly created position, and the head of the new unit.
ITD's organizational structure in 1985 included the Computing Center, the Office of Administrative Systems, the Center for Information Technology Integration, and the Office of Instructional Technology. Carolyn Autrey-Hunley served as Computing Center director after Aaron Finerman's retirement in 1986 until 1990, when Computing Center functions were absorbed into a new ITD administrative structure made up of the following units: Resource Administration, Networking Systems, Research Systems, Instructional Technology Systems, and the Assistance and Support Center.
Directors of the Computing Center
1959-1978 Robert F. C. Bartels
1978-1986 Aaron Finerman
1986-1990 Carolyn Autrey-Hunley
Records of the Computing Center have been received in three major accessions ? 1994, 1996, and 2011. Arrangement of the records in each accession is intended to reflect complimentary series. Each accession is described separately, and there is some overlap between the two.
The 1994 accession of the Computing Center record group primarily documents the founding and operation of the University of Michigan Computing Center from 1959 to 1987. It also includes some information on computing activities at the university prior to the founding of the Computing Center, dating back as far as 1952. Researchers should note that there is overlap between this accession and 1996 accessions. There is also overlap with the Information Technology Division record group, particularly after 1986 when ITD was created to bring together the Data Systems Center and the Computing Center under the purview of the Provost for Academic Affairs.
The records, which were in a very disorganized state when accessioned into the archives, were arranged into eight series: Historical Files, Administrative Records, Topical File, MTS (Michigan Terminal System), Word Processing Project, Vendors, and Photographs.
The 1996 accessions from the Computing Center add 32 feet of additional material to the record group. The records bring (in various formats) both breadth and depth to the earlier accessions, filling in major gaps and adding new documentation. The records are organized into nine series, generally corresponding to the arrangement of the earlier accession: Administrative Records, Computer Files, MTS (Michigan Terminal System), Merit Network, MAD (Michigan Algorithm Decoder), Word Processing Project, Vendors, Software Contracts, and Topical Files. Researchers should note that there is considerable overlap between Computing Center accessions and the Information Technology record group, particularly between 1985 and 1990 and especially for financial material and major committees.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Computing Center.; Computers.; Michigan Terminal System.; Word processing.; University of Michigan. University Committee on Computer Policy and Utilization.; University of Michigan. Information Technology Division.; University of Michigan. Statistical Research Laboratory.; Bartels, R. C. F. (Robert Christian Frank); Finerman, Aaron.; International Business Machines Corporation.; Merit Network, Inc.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Historical Files 1952-1988
  The Historical Files (1952-1988) consist of two folders of articles, manuscripts, notes for presentations, and historical sketches on the history of the Computing Center and computing activity at the university. Many of the articles are photocopies from university publications.
  - Notes (Box 1)
    (historical sketches etc. on aspects of computing at Michigan)
  - Articles (Box 1)
    (manuscript and published material relating to history of the Computing Center)
- Administrative Records
  The Administrative Records series (3.5 linear ft., 1956-1987) includes subseries for Annual Reports, Committees, Budget Material, Buildings and Computing Sites, Organization and Planning, and Correspondence.
  - Annual Reports
    The Annual Reports, 1958/59-1968/69 include formal reports to the President (as part of the Horace H. Rackham School of Graduate Studies report) as well as a number of other reports on computer usage.
    - 1958-1968 (Box 1)
  - Committees
    The Committees subseries consists of minutes, agendas, and related material for the principal policy and management committees of the Computing Center. These include the UCCPU (University Committee on Computer Policy and Utilization), Committee "A," the Computing Center Advisory Committee, and the Computing Center Executive Committee, among others. The UCCPU was a university-wide committee charged with developing broad computing policy across campus. All purchases of major computing systems by academic and administrative units had to have UCCPU approval to insure some level of compatibility and coherent development. The UCCPU files in the Computing Center record group cover the years from 1979 to 1983. (Minutes for the years 1965 to 1977 are located in a separate UCCPU record group at the Bentley Library. See finding aid for "University of Michigan. University Committee on Computer Policy and Utilization.") The minutes document both broad policy questions and reviews of requests by university units to purchase particular computing systems. The Computing Center record group also includes files of several UCCPU subcommittees: Computer Ethics, 1979; Computing Center Priorities, 1979-1980; Micro-Computer Policy, 1983; and Word Processing, 1980.
    Committee "A" was established by director Aaron Finerman in 1978 to serve as the Computing Center's primary internal management committee and was composed of senior computing center administrators. The files, 1978-1986, (1.2 linear feet) include minutes, agendas, reports and correspondence. The Advisory Committee consisted of senior Computing Center staff plus six to eight other staff members who served on a rotating basis. The committee's function was to advise the director on operation of the Computing Center. The records, 1978 to 1980, include some long-range planning materials. The Executive Committee was created in 1959 to serve as the Computing Center's governing board. It was composed of the Computing Center director and university faculty and administrators. The committee files, dating from 1959 to 1966 and 1979 to 1985, provide an overview of Computing Center activities. The Review Committee files, 1984-1986, contain minutes, reports and correspondence relating to the university's review of the Computing Center.
    - Committee A
      - 1978-1984, 16 folders (Box 1)
      - 1985-July 1986, 4 folders (Box 2)
    - Advisory Committee 1978-1980, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Executive Committee
      - 1959-1966 (Box 2)
      - 1979-1984, 5 folders (Box 2)
    - Review Committee 1984-1986 (Box 2)
    - University Committee on Computer Policy and Use (UCCPU) (minutes prior to 1979 are in separate UCCPU record group)
      - Minutes 1979-March 1983, 7 folders (Box 2)
      - April 1983-1984, 3 folders (Box 3)
      - Subcommittee on Computer Ethics 1979 (Box 3)
      - Subcommittee on Computing Center Priorities 1979-1980 (Box 3)
      - Subcommittee on Micro-Computer Policy, Progress Report October 10, 1983 (Box 3)
      - Subcommittee on Word Processing 1980 (Box 3)
  - Budget Material
    The Budget Material subseries includes annual files covering the period from 1978/79 to 1985/86, and consist of income and expense data, a variety of graphs relating to the Computing Center budget and finances, and other background information, as well as correspondence concerning the budget process. The amount and quality of information varies from year to year.
    - 1978-1986, 9 folders (Box 3)
  - Buildings and Computing Sites 1959-1984
    The Buildings and Computing Sites subseries, 1959-1984, documents the physical locations of Computing Center activity beginning at the North University Building (NUB), 1959-1974; the planning, construction and dedication of the Computing Center on North Campus, 1966-1979; and the opening of the Michigan Union (UNYN) computing site, 1983. In addition there are several reports on Computing Center space needs and a 1983 proposal for development of student-faculty computing sites.
    - Computing Center
      - Construction Plans, Budgets, etc. 1966-1979, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Dedication, 1970-71 (includes CC dedication booklet) (Box 3)
      - Prospectus 1966 (Box 3)
      - Space Needs 1979-1984 (Box 3)
    - NUB (North University Building) Site 1959-1974 (Box 3)
    - Student-Faculty Computing Facility Proposal 1983 (Box 3)
    - UNYN (Michigan Union Site) 1983 (Box 3)
  - Organization and Planning 1956-1959
    The Organization and Planning subseries, 1956-1959 and 1970-1985, brings together a variety of files on the administrative development of the Computing Center and the internal planning process. The files have been arranged chronologically. The 1956-1959 folder includes various reports and proposals relating to numeric computing on campus and the establishment of the Computing Center. Files for later years include reports, correspondence, memoranda, and several formal planning documents.
    - Computing Center Planning
      - 1956-1959 (Box 4)
        (includes various reports and proposals relating to numeric computing on campus and the establishment of the computing center)
      - 1970-77 (Box 4)
        (misc. notes, charts, and detailed 1977 report on organization, hardware, software and services of the computing center)
      - 1978-1979 (mostly Long Range Planning Committee, a subcommittee of Committee A) (Box 4)
      - 1981-1984 (Box 4)
        (additional Long Range Planning Committee material)
      - 1982-1984 (Box 4)
        (Assorted notes and correspondence on planning issues)
      - 1983 Memo. of Understanding, CC and OAS (Box 4)
      - 1985
        - Strategic Planning Retreat (Box 4)
        - Reorganization (Box 4)
      - Three-Year Plans 1982-1987, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Correspondence 1979-1986
    The Correspondence subseries is divided into: General, 1979-1986; Electronic Mail printouts, 1983-1984; Charles Overberger, Vice President for Research, 1979-1984; Billy Frye, Vice President for Academic Affairs, 1980-1983; and Alfred Sussman, Dean of the Graduate School, 1983-1984. The General correspondence (3 folders) covers the full range of computing center activities while the bulk of the other files relate to administrative and budget matters.
    - General 1979-1987, 4 folders (Box 4)
    - E-Mail 1983-1984 (Box 4)
    - Frye, Billy 1980-1983 (Box 4)
    - Overberger, Charles 1979-1984, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Sussman, Alfred 1983-1984, 2 folders (Box 4)
- Topical File 1960-1986
  A number of subject oriented files have been brought together in the Topical File series (3 linear ft., 1960-1986). The series, which is arranged alphabetically, includes files on a variety of internal and external projects, various ad-hoc committees and task forces, and Computing Center relationships with other university units. Among the more significant are: Computing Center Policy, Ford Foundation "Computers in Engineering" Grant, MAD (Michigan Algorithm Decoder), MIDAC (Michigan Digital Automatic Computer), Software Engineering Institute, and Supercomputing.